Well, apparently all those herculean
efforts to find a compromise over the
issue of slavery were about as effective
as a jellyfish trying to blow up
balloons for a birthday party, you know,
so cuz they don't they don't have lungs,
so not effective, you know. Okay, guess
I need to cross Skyazone based comedy
off my list for hilarious video hooks.
Anyway, the compromise failed and that's
going to lead to civil war and that's
what this video is about. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milt, let's
get to it. Okay, so a couple of videos
ago we talked about the compromise of
1850 in which Henry Clay did his
fighting best to make a juicy
compromised sandwich that would put to
rest the broiling sectional tensions
over the expansion of slavery into the
West and that was 1850. And by 1860,
states began seceding from the Union and
that would cause the Civil War. So what
in the fresh heck happened in the
intervening decade? Well, there were two
more major attempts to solve the slavery
debate and those attempts made things
absolutely worse. First was the Kansas
Nebraska Act of 1854. So remember that
the Missouri Compromise of 1820
established that territories north of
the 3630 line would be closed to slavery
while those south of the line would
remain open to slavery. And most
important to remember is that this
agreement only applied to the territory
gained in the Louisiana purchase. But if
you've been following along during this
unit, you will no doubt remember that
after the Mexican-American War, the US
won roughly five metric buttloads of
land in the Mexican session and that
3630 business did not apply to that
territory. And that's what the
compromise of 1850 tried and ultimately
failed to settle. So the point is the
slavery question in all this land right
here had been altogether settled for 30
years. I mean pro-slavery and
anti-slavery folks had plenty of
problems, but this was not one of them.
But Illinois Senator Steven Douglas woke
up one morning and decided that he was
ready to make it a problem. Oh, and by
the way, if you want note guys to follow
along with this video and all my videos,
then that link is in the description.
Anyway, Douglas was real desirous to get
one of the nation's new transcontinental
railroads to pass through his state of
Illinois. that in order to do that, the
federal government would have to take
control of the unorganized territory
west of Illinois in order to complete
the route. And just in case you didn't
grow up in the golden age of
transcontinental railroads, let me just
tell you that having one of these sweet
bippies cross your state would mean a
whole lot of pocket cabbage for the
population in question. So that's why
southerners were competing with Douglas
for an alternative route for the
railroad that favored their states. So
what Douglas did to sweeten the deal for
his southern congressional brethren was
to introduce the Kansas Nebraska Act. It
proposed that two new territories be
formed from the unorganized territory,
namely Kansas and Nebraska. And the
population of each territory would
decide by popular sovereignty whether to
allow slavery. In other words, despite
the mandate of the Missouri compromise,
Douglas was willing to court southern
support by opening the possibility of
the expansion of slavery above the 3630
line. And ultimately, Douglas was
successful and the bill became law. And
while this made southerners happy, many
northerners were enraged since the law
overturned the Missouri Compromise and
served as evidence for the growing slave
power of the southern states. And I know
it might be hard to believe, but this
actually went very badly. As I mentioned
in previous videos, although the notion
of popular sovereignty seems like a good
idea and one that upholds the principles
of liberty, the practical implementation
of it was never clear-cut. Case in
point, it was now federal law that the
people of Kansas and Nebraska would vote
for themselves on the slavery question.
But Douglas never really explained how
this kind of voting would work. Nor did
he comment on several difficult issues
that would arise as a result of this
policy. For example, if a territory was
already home to a population of
slaveholders and it voted to abolish
slavery, then what would happen to the
enslaved people and the planters who
claimed ownership over them? And all
those unanswered questions led to a
proper bloodbath when it came time for
Kansas to become a state in 1854. So
like 5 minutes after the Kansas Nebraska
Act passed, thousands of pro-slavery and
anti-slavery advocates flooded into
Kansas from surrounding states in order
to sway the vote. In fact, so many
people were arriving into Kansas by the
day that it was nearly impossible for
the authorities to determine who was
eligible to vote and who was not. It
would kind of be like if in the next
presidential election, hundreds of
thousands of Canadians rushed across the
border and voted for a US president that
they thought would be best for Canada.
And I'm sure they would apologize
profusely for it and run back across the
border for a hearty Tim Horton's
breakfast, but you know, you get the
point. So although the majority of
canons wanted to enter the Union as a
free state, border ruffians who had
flooded in from Missouri tipped the vote
toward making Kansas a slave state.
massive fail for popular sovereignty.
Now, it was pretty clear to everyone
that the illegal pro-slavery voters had
upended the will of the canon people.
And as a result, the rival factions
established two opposing state
governments. The proslavery Kansas
government was set up in Shauny Mission,
while the anti-slavery government was
established in Lawrence. And not long
after, pro-slavery canons attacked the
anti-slavery government in Lawrence,
which resulted in the death of one
person and a significant amount of
property destruction. And battles
between the two factions raged for
months, and in the end, 50 Americans
were dead in what became known as
bleeding Kansas. It was an on-ag again
off-again conflict that lasted until
1859. And what it told Americans is that
the slavery debate was only going to be
settled by blood. And that commitment
was on display once again in 1856 in the
very chambers of the US Senate in the
caning of Charles Sumner. So in that
year, Republican Senator Charles Sumner
delivered a blistering speech in
Congress denouncing slavery and the
rising slave power in the South. And he
was not vague in his denunciation. No,
Siri, he was about as subtle as a
stomach pump. So Sumar directed his
attack against southern politicians
among the planter elite, specifically
Andrew Butler of South Carolina. Now, as
it turned out, Butler's nephew, a House
representative by the name of Preston
Brooks, was in no mood to abide such an
insult to his family's honor. So, Brooks
entered the Senate chambers, walked up
to Sumner, and beat the man with his
cane until he was nearly dead. Now, not
surprisingly, northerners were outraged
by this brutality and held Sumner up as
a martyr for the free soil cause.
Southerners, on the other hand, held up
Brooks as a hero, and in fact, Brooks
received dozens of new canes sent to him
by southern supporters. And look, side
note here, sometimes students ask me if
our current political moment is as bad
and divisive as it's ever been. answer.
No. Like until our Congress people are
beating each other to death with blunt
objects. It could be worse. And speaking
of getting worse, it's now time to
introduce you to a Supreme Court case
that really turned up the heat on the
sectional tension over slavery. So in
1857, the court ruled on DreadScott v.
Sanford. And here are the details in
brief. Dread Scott was an enslaved man
whose owner had taken him to live in
Illinois and Wisconsin, both of which
were free states. And by Scott's
reckoning, if he had lived on free soil,
that meant he ought to be a free man.
And so he sued his owner for freedom.
But the Chief Justice Roger Tony, an
altogether pro-slavery man, delivered
the decision which ruled that an
enslaved person was not a citizen and
therefore had no legal rights, not least
the right to sue in court. And yeah,
that's bad, but not altogether
unexpected for the time. But the real
egg in the sock was that this decision
established the precedent that
slaveholders could not be deprived of
their property even in free states. And
in case you still don't feel the heat of
that explosive claim, let me say it
plain. It meant that in effect, every US
state and territory was now open to the
expansion of slavery. And so as a
result, northerners cried foul at the
further undoing of the Missouri
Compromise and were angered yet again at
more evidence of the growing slave power
in the South. I mean, the fugitive slave
law had already required northerners to
participate in the perpetuation of
slavery, but after the Dread Scott case,
there was literally no square inch of
American soil that was safe from the
expansion of the institution. So the
point is, slavery had finally and fully
broken the US into two rival regional
factions. And that's going to have one
more big effect. So before the 1850s,
the two political parties of the United
States had members and supporters from
the entire nation, even if their
constituencies were unequally
distributed regionally. For example, the
Democrats had both a northern faction
and a southern faction, etc. However, by
1854, the second party system was
falling apart, and in its place,
political parties arose that represented
the strict sectional division of the
nation. So in the congressional election
of 1854, the wigs lost real bad since
the public perceived that they had
utterly failed to stop the slave power
from taking over the federal government.
and then the American party or the no
nothings won some impressive victories.
But once slavery overshadowed the
immigrant problem, the party's power
began to wne. Therefore, during the 1854
election, the new party system included
the pro-slavery Democrats and the free
soil Republicans. And the point to
remember about these parties is that
they catered almost exclusively to
sectional interests. The Republicans
were concentrated in the north and
advocated the free soil position, which
is to say they agreed to leave slavery
alone where it existed and prevent the
expansion of slavery. The Democrats were
concentrated in the south and advocated
for the position of states rights and
the expansion of slavery into the west.
However, I should mention that there
were internal divisions within each
party as well. Like some Republicans
didn't want to be associated with
violent radicals like John Brown, while
Democrats struggled to please northern
and southern factions in their party.
Regardless, in the presidential election
of 1860, this sectional political split
would ultimately lead the US right into
civil war. Well, okay. You can click
here to watch my other videos from unit
5, or you can click here to grab my
video note guides, which are going to
help you get all the contents of this
course firmly crammed into your brain
fold. I'm glad you came around and I'll
catch you on the flipflop.